[Music]
a
hello everybody uh apologies for that
there was a glitch in The Matrix but we
are back I hope you're doing well
and welcome to this latest episode of
the ask ofit show this is episode 199 we
are just one episode away from uh the
double century mark so thank you so much
all of you for being uh part of this
this uh this wonderful ad adventure and
thank you all of thank you to all of you
who are on the live chat live stream
right now let me see who all is there
today is the live uh today is the
Science episode we're going to talk
about science I'm going to take
questions from the comments and I'm
going to answer the best of the
questions that you've asked so let me
see who all is there on the live chat I
can say suas RI
parav uh Kenneth tan from the
Philippines Hello nice to see you sir
dungar Singh Johan great to see you by
anit Akash Pand abishek sastav bigum
Kamala Harris
Al three way S2 samit statement even a
god of feminist cannot defeat
uh bam GK by GS M MD swag Yash Pand
Abdullah fairy tale SAS REI parasat
kundu VM tube TPU Master Anan Pai basar
kayal Al B Karan nwat hello Raptor J
Tano
chra du
mangon ishan Singh Geno as curiosity
Diaz hello Cosmic gaming 8 7781 cookie D
Joy mukarji Vladimir chavda Moana Ray
Roy Naga mokit Raa ainash suasi parasu
n SW mahik niharika
Gupta har du um so many other people
random skull hello
Shas and so many other people zuban eang
GK om ker hello and everybody else I
won't be able to greet you all but let's
get going with the questions I'm going
to take questions first of all from the
comments and once those are done I'm
going to take some questions from the
live chat uh once those are done so let
us see what questions we have what
questions you have asked in the comments
and let me see how many of those I can
take I'll take as many as possible what
is the first question it is by shot 4411
and the question is tell us something
about the observer effect the obser
observer effect of quantum
mechanics uh the I don't know if you
guys remember but there used to be in
the 1990s a song called Shy Guy shy guy
by a lady called Diana King very famous
song in the 1990s I was a kid back then
I don't think anyone remembers that
today it's kind of an obscure classic
song but that song is kind of
appropriate for the observer effect
imagine that you have a friend imagine
you have a friend who is really shy and
this friend of yours behaves differently
when he or she knows that someone's
watching them so the observer effect is
kind of like that but it happens in the
quantum world so the observer effect
describes how the act of observing
something or measuring something can
change what is being observed so for
example let's say that you trying to
check the air pressure in your bike tire
you have a bike you want to check if the
pressure is what the pressure is so you
have to take a pressure garge you have
to insert it you to press it into the
valve in in the in the bike tire and
when you do that to check the pressure a
tiny bit of air escapes from the tire
when you insert that right so this means
that the very Act of measuring the
pressure of the bike tire slightly
changes the pressure in the tire
this is this is an example of the
observer effect in the real world that
we inhabit in the classical world in the
everyday world that we inhabit the tools
and the methods that we use to observe
or measure something can can
inadvertently end up changing affecting
and changing what we trying to measure
what we're trying to observe what we're
trying to study imagine you have a glass
of water you have a glass of water okay
and you want to measure the temperature
of this glass of water water so what are
you going to do you're going to take a
thermometer you're going to insert it
into the water now I can guarantee you
that your thermometer is going to be at
a different temperature than the water
slightly cooler slightly warmer whatever
it's it there's no way it will be
exactly at the same temperature as the
water so when you put the thermometer in
the water it will slightly change the
water's
temperature okay so once again just by
trying to observe or measure something
you end you end up changing the system
or changing the thing that you're trying
to observe now when it comes to Quantum
Mechanics the the ultra microscopic the
hyper microscopic world this effect
becomes even more noticeable and
important let's say you you got a super
tiny particle let's say you have an
electron a single electron and you want
to know where it is and how fast it is
moving that's all you want to know you
know there's an electron in a box let's
say and you want to know exactly where
it is and how fast it is moving so how
do you do that well you're going to try
and see it right you're going to try and
bounce light off it but in the ultra
macroscopic Quantum World light comes in
the form of photons are these little
packets or you can say particles of
light massless particles of light that
have momentum and energy so you're going
to take this these photons you're going
to try and bounce them of the electron
but the electron is so small that the
very Act of a photon bouncing off it is
going to change its position it's going
to knock it off it of it of its position
it will change its velocity change its
trajectory the electron may even end up
absorbing this Photon so just by trying
to observe or measure observe the
electron or measure its properties you
end up changing what the electron is
doing and the changing the very uh
nature of the
electron so this is like trying to see
what your shy friend is
doing but as soon as you peek at your sh
shy friend they start acting differently
okay so in other in other words the very
Act of measuring or observing something
in the quantum World actually changes
the thing that you're trying to observe
or measure and that makes it really hard
to know exactly what's going on because
the very Act of observation changes what
you're observing and it can mess mess up
your mess things up so that essentially
is the observer effect hopefully makes a
little bit of sense the way I have
explained
it next question is by Tech rumor how to
explain wormholes to Children the
universe is a sphere so why fold paper
for the explanation what is the proof
that it exists okay the universe well
the observable universe you can think of
it as a sphere but we don't know if this
universe is spherical okay so the the
observable universe the the OBS the the
cosmic Horizon is kind of spherical and
we are at the center but that's merely
what we can observe the the actual
Universe maybe is most likely way bigger
and we don't know what the actual shape
is but now let's let's talk about verm
holes what are verm holes and you don't
want me to use the analogy of the sheet
of paper and you poke a hole through
that right because it's it's it's an
over overused cliche it's like flogging
a dead horse so okay so how do I explain
wormholes for children let's imagine the
universe okay as a giant bowel of
noodles you know noodles Maggie noodles
ramen spaghetti whatever imagine that
the universe is a big giant ball of
noodles and each noodle each individual
noodle each strand of noodles represents
one specific path through space and time
so the universe is this giant ball with
with a tremendous number of paths
through space and time and each strand
of noodles each noodle is is one
specific path through space and time so
normally if you want to go go from one
end of the universe one part of the
bowel to another part of the bowel you
have to walk along one of the one of
these curved Parts one of these noodle
strands so imagine that you are an ant a
tiny ant and you are standing on one of
these noodles one of the noodle strands
and you are at one location and you want
to get to another location so you're
going to have to crawl like an ant
because you're an ant you're going to
have to crawl over this Noodle and it's
going to be a long winding path and it's
going to have twists and turns and it's
going to take you a long time but what
if you have a shortcut what if there
exists a
shortcut which allows you to reach the
other part of the universe like that so
it's it's like you found a way to poke a
hole through the noodles and this hole
connects two distant parts of the
universe bowel
directly so instead of crawling over
along the entire noodle you you the ant
can just zip into this hole and come out
on the other side way faster than if you
had to travel the entire long path so
that is kind of a wormhole in a real in
the in the real Universe the Wormhole
could theoretically uh connect two
distant points in space time through a
shortcut so it it gives you a potential
shortcut across tremendous Cosmic
distances and possibly even through time
itself Let's uh use a different analogy
imagine the universe is a giant
playground okay kids playground and in
this playground you got lots of paths
and lots of roads and lots of routes
that you can take to go from one place
to another in the playground but these
paths and Roads and all they are very
long and winding now think of this think
of a wormhole as a secret shortcut that
connects to far away places in
playground directly it's kind of like a
hidden tunnel so instead of walking and
taking this long twisting winding path
you just jump into the tunnel and
instantly appear at your destination
imagine you're playing a video
game and uh your character in this video
game can use a special portal and this
portal instantaneously transports you
from one part of the G game world into
another part of the game world
and you can skip all the obstacles skip
all the
dangers not dangers you can skip all the
all the obstacles and it saves you a lot
of time so you have this magic portal
which instantly trans transports you
from one part of the game world to
another you skip all the obstacles saves
you a tremendous amount of time so
Wormhole Works in a similar way it's
like a shortcut across it's like a
shortcut through space and time it
allows you to travel vast distances in a
very short time but just like in some
video games where portals can be
unstable and portals can be dangerous
wormholes if they exist might be
extremely unstable and they may require
conditions for them to stay open that we
don't quite fully understand yet you may
need exotic matter inside the Wormhole
throat to keep it open you may need
something even weirder like cosmic
strings inside to keep keep it open keep
the throat open so worm holes overall
are mathematically
possible solutions of the Einstein field
equations uh they are mathematically
possible according to the the theory of
general relativity but we have not found
any evidence that they actually exist
thus far and creating a wormhole would
probably require tremendous amounts of
energy and maintaining a wormhole
keeping it open would also probably
require exotic forms of matter and
energy that we don't even know are
possible in the universe so that is how
I would explain wormhole
to
kids okay clasher obas says please
explain Rock and science rocket science
haha I think this question was asked as
a joke but let me take it seriously
let's understand what rocket science is
well rocket science isn't actually
science it's engineering it's applied
science and what is the the problem
we're trying to solve in rocket science
in in rocketry let's say what you want
to do is you want to transport something
from point A to point B in a very short
amount of time and ideally you can use a
rocket to deliv deliver a payload from
point A to point B on the surface of the
planet
or more likely you want to get into
space so maybe you want to place a
payload into Earth's orbit or maybe you
want to go to the moon or maybe you want
to go to Mars or you maybe you want to
go to the Andromeda galaxy so you want
to go beyond the Earth okay you want to
travel into space so how you do that
that's the problem you want to solve I
want I have this
requirement I want to get into space so
how do I do it that's the problem you
want to solve and that's where rocket
engineering comes in it's actually
rocket engineering not rocket science
it's not rocket scientists it's rocket
Engineers so what what you do is you
need what you need is you need a vehicle
that can take you into space now for
that you will have to overcome the
escape velocity of the Earth or let's
say you Place something in orbit around
the Earth okay in that case you don't
need to have a speed in excess of the
escape Velocity but you need to have
orbital speed so you need to get to a
certain amount of altitude and then you
cannot just go straight up you to go in
that direction and you to miss the Earth
and constantly fall and all that so you
need a vehicle that can achieve
tremendous velocities that is
aerodynamic which can uh which which
will not burn up because of friction
with the atmosphere the heating of the
atmosphere and all that so what so for
that you need the right kind of uh
structure the right kind of uh material
which is typically metal and and
composits you need the right kind of
aerodynamic shape and you need the right
kind of fuel you need fuel with a very
high
impulse okay uh kerosene which is
aviation fuel won't do it doesn't have
that much impulse uh petroleum and
whatever else won't do you need
something with much higher impulse so
you could use hypergolic fuel FS which
are extremely toxic or you could use
Simple liquid hydrogen liquid oxygen
cryogenic fuels and so on so all of
these problems are solved in in a
variety of methods using engineering and
that is rocket science and if you want
to travel to other planets and so on so
forth you have to understand Celestial
Celestial mechanics which obviously is
is nothing but a branch of Newtonian
mechanics classical mechanics you don't
need to use quantum theory um general
relativity Etc in that you may no you
don't need general relativity you can
send human beings safely to the moon and
bring them back without ever resorting
to general relativity you can do that
just by using Newtonian mechanics so all
of this is rocket science all right that
that that is the problem that rocket
science seeks to solve and it has
engineering Solutions so you it involves
the study of aerodynamics and the
application of aerodynamics uh the
application of various kinds of fuels
multiple staging Rockets if required uh
you know deployment of payloads into
orbit achieving orbital velocity
injecting your vehicle in a specific
orbit whether it's a polar orbit whether
it is a lisu orbit whether it is a what
is it called uh geocentric orbit and so
on so forth or a transfer orbit into a
different maybe lunar transfer orbit or
whatever and so on orbital raising
Maneuvers the a whole lot that that is
involved in all this so all of this
taken together is what is colloquially
called rocket science is actually rocket
engineering all
right okay swapnil Mishra says why do
modern fruits and vegetables look and
taste so different from their wild
ancestors and what caused this change to
occur yeah it's a good good question I
mean modern vehic fruits and vegetabl
they have evolved over time for example
let me put something on the screen I
mean there is something called the giant
red
giant red
banana check it out so you know the
fruits that we are aware of come in a
variety of of different cultivars and
all that look at this thing for example
this is called a c banana look at it
Kasa
banana banana and that looks quite
different from the bananas that we are
familiar with but in in yet it is a kind
of banana but it's not something that we
really use or or are even much aware of
and when it comes to the bananas the
ancestor of the banana plant or the
banana fruit uh was very different from
the the banana of fruit that we are
familiar with it was much smaller and it
had large seeds and it had very little
edible flesh and all that so it all U
happened through selective cultivation
when when our ancestors thousands of
years ago dis discovered that certain
plants have some good qualities and they
they can they are good candidates for
for food then they started cultivating
them and they started selectively
breeding them just like we have bred
various uh various uh breeds of dogs I
mean if you look at you know dogs the
dogs come in so many shapes and sizes
some don't even look like dogs I mean
their wolf ancestors would be I would
say ashamed to imagine that these These
are their descendants those poodles and
those huas and Pomeranians and whatnot
those toy looking like n what uh sausage
dogs or whatever I mean it's hard to
imagine that these are descended from
wolves right but that's the case so
that's what humans are capable of what
time we can create various uh breeds of
plants animals vegetables fruits
whatever as per uh our our requirements
and our tastes so that's what we've done
and obviously everything evolves over
time if you look at Homo sapiens the the
archaic Homo sapiens from jbel HUD in
North Africa from 400,000 years ago I
mean they are anatomically modern humans
they have the same skeletal structure as
uh you and me as ually but their facial
features are a little more primitive
with the little larger eye eye ridges
and slightly more I don't know different
kind of facial characteristics and all
that uh so Evolution happens over time
it happens naturally and when the human
beings get involved then Evolution can
be accelerated by selective
breeding so overall that's why things
change that's why fruits have evolved
and vegetables have evolved especially
those that we humans have been
interested in and then you have things
like what the Green Revolution that
happened in India in which certain
cultivars of wheat certain cultivars of
rice were prioritized over everything
else that kind of you know stunted the
the natural diversity of of various uh
cereals in the country it kind of put uh
the millets ETC on a back on the back
foot it almost make them obsolete now
they're taking making a comeback so yeah
that's how it goes It's all about
choices that humans make which has a
long-term lasting and very very
pronounced impact on the way the
ecosystem the environment evolves so
that's why modern fruits and vegetables
look and taste different from their wild
ancestors I mean wheat think about wheat
wheat is a grass it's it's it's a form
of grass sugar cane is a form of grass
but we selected these plants for certain
properties and we bred them and that's
how if you look at Wild wheat which
still still exists in some parts of the
world it looks very different from the
wheat that we are familiar with and
similarly wild sugar cane would be much
thinner and shorter than the typical
sugar cane that we have in the fields
for cultivation so it's because of
selective breeding done by humans that
all these changes
happened next question is by rajouri gon
8396 why does Australia have such an
enormous variety of venomous and
poisonous animals as compared to other
continents I think Australian animals
get too much of a bad rap I know there
are certain very scary animals let's go
back to Google what about the inland
taipan I mean they have some
really uh what on Earth am I doing one
second they have some really really
scary dangerous
Etc uh animals for example the Inland
taian is probably I believe the world's
uh most venomous snake perhaps one of
the world's most venomous snakes the
Inland typan that's an Australian
snake
um it is ETC yeah
Australia then you have something called
the box jellyfish box jelly fish that is
another frighteningly dangerous
jellyfish and uh if you are bitten by
that it can be fatal and it's extremely
painful extremely dangerous and uh you
don't want to be near this okay so there
is that then Australia has various kinds
of uh very scary sharks including the
great white shark which is the number
two predator in the oceans the great
white shark great white shark which is
the number two predator in the oceans
not number one and the number one is not
the Megalodon it's the Orca the killer
whale what else do the Australians have
they have got uh what red backs red back
spider red back spiders and various
other kinds of spiders I mean imagine
this spider is as you can see it's
killed a snake
here and then what else do they have uh
what else can I think of the Australians
have a number of very
scary rather scary animals and such
species but overall if you look at the
other animals in Australia like the
marsupials kangaroos they have like at
least a couple of species of kangaroos
they have Wales they have
koalas and they have all kinds of
harmless animals as well really harmless
animals the kangaroos are kind of feisty
they they are known to box and uh they
kind of are territorial in nature
they'll they won't be happy the
especially the large kangaroos if if you
INE into into the territory and so on
but all okay yeah I forgot the
crocodiles the the saltwater crocodiles
let's put that on the
screen so that's not exactly an
Australian crocodile salt water
crocodile um that's a crocodile that's
even found in in India okay in the
eastern Indian Ocean region but it is a
gigantic crocodile and this is also
found in Northern Australia northern
eastern stria Etc very very large
gigantic monstrous crocodile the
saltwater
crocodile and I'm sure I'm missing a few
of these wonderful creatures but uh that
is the deal but they also have a lot of
harmless creatures so why so one thing I
would agree with is that Australia has
rather unique animals I mean you don't
find marsupials anywhere else in the
world apart from Australia and and and
Tasmania right marsupial they had you
had the hene the Tasmanian Tiger which
went extinct uh you have the what is it
called the red what devil Tasmanian
Devil which is also in Australia very
it's got a really really weird way of
shrieking at night really scary that's
why it's called the devil you have the
cabur bird that has an incredible
vocalization that is that too is scary
if you if you are not used to it and so
on um the thing is that Australia if you
look at the map okay we haven't seen the
map today I usually don't crack out the
map in in science streams but let's do
it Maps let me open that and uh put that
on the screen give me a second so what
we're going to do is we're going to take
a look at the map I'm going to go to the
Globe view okay so we're going to look
at Australia and you can see that it's
kind of isolated it's it's near Papa
yini Indonesia but it's kind of isolated
in the southern hemosphere far away from
most other you know
large real estates essentially and the
Animals here have evolved mostly in
isolation from other parts of the world
um so maybe that's the reason why they
have evolved differently in Australia
and Australia also has a very unique
kind of climate it has cold climate in
the South it has forests and mountains
it even even has snow somewhere or the
other I believe in New South Wales and
it has a very large desert region as you
can see it's baren a lot of it is Barren
so it's got a very unique uh terrain and
climate and that's why I would imagine
the animals have evolved here in
isolation for hundreds of thousands of
years and that's why they have evolved
in in rather unique
ways but I wouldn't say that Australia
has more dangerous venomous poisonous
animals and species than and let's say
other parts of the world in India you
have a whole lot of poisonous scary
animals you have the Cobra the standard
Indian cobra you have the spectacle
Cobra you have the king cobra you have
the the Russell's Viper you have various
kinds of pythons you have scorpions in
India rather scary scorpions and whatnot
I mean you've got really scary animals
in India you have gigantic bears at
least three species of bears we have in
India be look very fluffy and very nice
but trust me you don't want to be near
bears bears can be really really
dangerous and they incredibly powerful
Tigers stay away from bears so you have
that you have tigers obviously you have
lions in India you have hyenas and
whatnot so it's not like Australia is
something special every part of the
world has its predators and all that but
it's true that Australian animals have
evolved differently and they have rather
unique species over there because of the
relative isolation of of Australia and
uh the
and the unique kind of climate and
terrain that Australia is endowed
with
okay anti-human says what makes you say
that the American Military or
multinational corporations have egi
artificial general intelligence in their
Labs if they have it then why don't they
deploy it okay why do I say this it's
because we have known throughout history
that whenever new technology emerges it
is over always uh used first by the
military and the government of the
nation or culture or civilization where
the technology emerges and technology is
guarded guarded jealously it's not
distributed out freely for everybody to
use it is guarded jealously and history
tells you that whenever there have been
conflicts it's always the
technologically Superior side that that
that
prevails you know in in Warfare It's
always technology and Superior
technology and Superior Tactics that
prevails not Superior
bravery I mean in movies they talk about
bravery of humans and all that but in
the real world it's not about bravery
it's about Superior technology tactics
strategies and all that so when you have
something Superior you're going to
you're going to hold it you will not
make it available to the rest of the
world you will not even speak about it
think about the stealth technology that
the Americans had since the 1960s it was
first spoken about in in public in in
the late 80s and the first time it was
announced shown to the public was
probably the early '90s or thereabouts
but they had it for decades what about
MV technology multiple
independently whatever targetable
vehicles uh those also where where where
classified technology for such a long
time there is so much that has been
classified for a very long time there is
technology today that you have never
heard of that I have never heard of but
it exists so the The Cutting Edge
bleeding edge technology is always kept
secret okay why do we have so many UFO
sightings maybe these are futuristic
aircraft that are being tested and some
sometimes people spot them right so
there's there's always that I mean
history has told history tells us
history of the 20th century tells us
that so much technology was kept hidden
for a very long
time now so that's why I believe that
whatever we if if AI is known to exist
today then what we are seeing is merely
the tip of the iceberg and what really
exists out there deep under the secret
layers of secrecy in in the US military
or Department of whatever thing military
or or various multinational corporations
or American corporations I I imagine
what they have is at least 100 times
more powerful maybe many orders of
magnitude more powerful which would
which would essentially mean artificial
general intelligence or even ASI
artificial super intelligence that's why
I say that that the I say that it it is
possible that this may exist now the
question is why haven't they deployed it
my dear friends who tells you that they
haven't deployed it if they have it it
may be deploy like I said they may have
deployed various futuristic aircraft and
sometimes you get some glimpse of
glimpse of it and you think it's an it's
UFO maybe lots of such things have been
deployed and we are not aware of them
when you deploy something you don't
announce it to the world and and and
show it to everyone you you deployed
steal maybe everything is being observed
right now maybe every government is
compromised right now maybe every bank
account is compromised right now maybe
every prime minister and president
whatever they're doing right now they
they are being monitored in real
time maybe your new every nation's
nuclear program is is being monitored in
real time maybe everything has been
being monitored in real time and
everything is known but we don't know
about it because it's secret maybe it's
all deployed think about it I mean use
your thought process use your
imagination and I'm not talking about
imagining magic and Fantasies and fairy
tales this is all logical it is
consistent with
science so it is possible that AGI
already exists it is also possible that
ASI may already exist artificial super
intelligence and if it exists it is
being used in its been deployed but you
don't know about
it all
right Anand Chandra sharan 1969 says I'm
working in an IT company and already see
that AI is gradually replacing human
effort and even causes job
loss do you think that in the
future AI artificial intelligence will
supersede human minds and become a
company friendly resource
in that case is the AI easily manageable
and cost
saving um I see it rather differently I
I agree with you AI is is already being
used widely it's used as widespread this
stupidest see look I'm sorry I shouldn't
say that look in a
company the real performers the real the
employees see let's say you have 100
comp 100 employees in your company the
there's going to be 10 guys or girls who
are the real performers who really Drive
uh whatever is happening so about about
five or 10 are the real performers maybe
20 are are the top level Talent then uh
another 20 or 30 are are okay level
talent and then there'll be like 30 40%
who are absolutely uh they should be
replaced that's generally how it is so
there is a significant percentage no
matter which company your in of of you
will have employees 30 40% at least who
are not real performers and who are
actually redundant and replaceable at
any given point in time those people are
the ones that AI will essentially can
replace right now there's so much that
AI can do that essentially makes people
significantly redundant especially those
who are not creative and not really
talented and not really hardworking and
even if they are hardworking if they
don't have that special talent then eii
can can replace the right now I mean if
you want to do research today you know
then you you don't need to hire research
assistants just use AI you know whatever
chat GPD 3.5 or 4.5 or or or or Gro or
Cloe or whatever these AIS can do a
stellar job as research assistants you
got to get the paid version and you can
do as many queries as suppose as you
want so yeah AI is already beginning to
make human beings redundant especially
the low skilled human beings and once
you have robotics coming into the
picture there going to make a lot of the
labor force redundant and because
robotics is way more efficient as than
humans and because robotics because
robots don't need to sleep they can work
24 by7 so it's it's it's going to be
it's going to be a paradigm shift in uh
in the
workforce so yes I agree with you that
AI is gradually replacing human effort
it's causing job losses already
uh so do I think that in the future AI
will supersede human Minds yes yes very
soon there's going to be very few fields
in which AI cannot outperform humans
right now ai can create music AI can
create all kinds of art I mean you can
tell you know if you have the eye for it
that this is AI art but for most people
it's good enough I mean beautiful art
you can produce art in the style of Wang
go or Picasso or whoever you want any
kind of art you know you can just give
it what you want and going to create art
in in that shape and form and in that
style music I'm sure the music isn't
like Soul stirring music but it's it's
good enough music so it's it's it's
going to put all but the best artists
out of commission and so much more so we
already are seeing this and when it
comes to you know tasks that don't
require a lot of intelligence AI is
already there and soon you will have AGI
which means AI an AI that is like
which is the equivalent of a person
person with 140 150 IQ and that person
can do essentially anything speak any
language you want translate in real time
give you ideas disagree with you and and
give you better suggestions and and
things like that that's that's AGI
artificial gener intelligence and then
soon you will have ASI artificial super
intelligence which is Way Beyond AGI
it's like having a person with an IQ of
300 or 400 and then it will it will
supersede anything you can do it'll go
way Way Beyond what the human mind is
capable of it's it's it's like Einstein
on steroids and and creatin and every
drug you can
imagine okay you you multiply Einstein
and raanan and leard Oiler and everybody
and you multiply that by a thousand
maybe that's what your ASI is going to
be like so that's what it will do
eventually will AI become company
friendly resource look if your company
is
is is paying for the AI if your company
is a customer of a company then it may
not really be company friendly it's
going to be that the it's going to be
friendly to the company that created it
that owns it but if your company has
created the AI and and owns the AI then
it's going to be hopefully in your
control okay so it's not going to be
friendly to anyone apart from those who
have created it and own it and hopefully
control it okay it may not be easily
manageable it will definitely be
cost-saving it may cut all your costs
but it will C it cut it will make people
immensely Rich only those who own the AI
everybody else will be out of job and
then they'll be wonder what what is
going to be done about
them uh yeah and we may soon be there
AGI ASI may already exist in secret so
we may be at the the the cusp of of the
greatest inflection point in human
history and we probably don't we unable
to see what's coming it could come
anytime so yeah that's that's how I see
it Malik said says is it possible to
connect large AI models to track rocket
Pathways projectiles and their motion
and improve it absolutely for large AI
models projectile motion is
Trivial large AI models can can can
model entire weather systems they can
model climate they can look far into the
future you know like weeks into the
future months into the future when it
comes to predicting climate patterns you
take AI you merge that with super
Computing capabilities and a obviously
needs a tremendous amount of resources
Computing resources gpus and all that it
can do that so when it can do that
what's what are rocket Pathways and
projectile motion that's that's child
child level stuff for AI yes so what AI
will be used for is is war gaming
nuclear nuclear
warfare okay let's say I I launch
hypothetically okay let's say I am a
superpower and I launched the first
strike on my on he he I who I hate the
most okay and he who I hate the most has
more nukes than me and he's going to
retaliate so how do we war game it and
in what by what way by what strategies
by by employing what strategy and
tactics can I turn this into a war a
nuclear exchange that is survivable for
me but not for
him so that's that's the kind of War
gaming a can do and it can find I'm sure
uh solutions that nobody may have
thought of so projectile motion rocket
track paths and all that that is that is
Trivial for AI that it can do in its
sleep
essentially all right prala says what
are cryogenic engines what makes them
different from other engines and why are
they used only in Rockets what are
cryogenic engines so essentially
cryogenics and cryogenic engines are
engines that use extremely low
temperature fuels okay cryogenic engines
are rocket engines that use propellants
fuels that are in the liquid state and
that are at extremely low temperatures
like minus 150 or something degrees
Centigrade so a very standard typical
cryogenic fuel are liquid hydrogen as
the fuel and liquid oxygen as the
oxidizer you bring them together you
know you spark the ignition thing it's
going to give you a tremendous amount of
energy as the exothermic reaction energy
as the output and the waste product
product that is expelled out is simply
water vapor H2O okay so that is a that
is a great example of a very standard
cryogenic fuel liquid hydrogen as the
fuel and liquid oxygen as the oxidizer
okay so that's what a cryogenic engine
is now what are the key differences of
cryogenic engines from other engines so
the first very clear
difference between cryogenic engines and
standard other standard engines is that
the cryogenic engines uh are they
operate at extremely low temperatures so
probably usually below minus 150 degrees
Celsius so when you see a rocket whether
that is on the Launchpad and it's
waiting to be launched you will see it
is it is sweating and it is steaming
right all this steam is coming off it
it's not steam it is extremely cold
condensation and when the locket rocket
because the fuel inside is is extremely
cold minus 150 - 160- 170° c so it's
going to you know you will have a layer
of ice that that forms on the surface of
the rocket and if if the if the air is
is humid then you will see all the
entire rocket steaming away and when the
rocket finally takes off you'll see all
this ice and everything falling off it
so that's because of the incredibly low
temperature that the rocket has because
that's the cryogenic propellent so the
first key difference is the temperature
tremendously low temperatures second
efficiency okay so cryogenic engines
offer extremely high specific impulse
which is a measure of the of the Rockets
efficiency and it has very high specific
impulse compared to other liquid or
solid propellent Rockets So if you have
a rocket that uses uh let's say
hypergolic fuels which is solid
propellant usually
or some other fuel let's say hydren or
something hydren is not bad overall but
cryogenics are are they have higher
specific impulse higher efficiency now
if you have a an engine a rocket engine
which is extremely cold fuel coming in
and an extremely hot exhaust exhaust
going out then you need extremely
sophisticated systems for storing the
propellent the liquid propul liquid
hydrogen liquid oxygen for pumping the
propeller into the engine for cooling
the engine because the moment the engine
ignites it has extraordinarily high
temperatures so it's going to you it's
going to need a tremendously
sophisticated set of systems to do this
so it's extremely complex okay so that's
the deal with with the kenic engines so
it's primarily used primarily used in
Rockets okay because of the high
performance and because of its
efficiency when it comes to space
applications and the cogenic engines are
typically not used in other vehicles
other applications first of all because
storage is very challenging you know
storing liquid hydrogen and liquid
oxygen at incredibly low temperatures is
almost impossible for day-to-day use how
do you do that okay it's it's almost
impossible in everyday
applications um secondly the
availability of these propellant I mean
cryogenic propellant you can go go to
gas station get and get liquid hydrogen
liquid oxygen because it's it's it's not
readily available at all because it
needs to be kept at incredibly low
temperatures and it takes a lot of uh
effort and various specialized processes
to to to separate hydrogen and oxygen
from water and all that so the
propellent isn't readily available and
obviously the the engines are incredibly
complex which means they're incredibly
expensive very costly so these systems
are way too expensive and way too
complex for day-to-day applications
non-space applications and these are the
reasons why cryogenic engines are only
used in rockets and probably nowhere
else got
it Karan nalat says what are black holes
made of is a black hole really a hole in
the fabric of SpaceTime or is a black
hole a solid object just like other
planets yeah that's a great question
what's a black hole made of well we
don't quite
know but I could construct a black hole
out of anything look when it comes to uh
let's say the simplest black hole of all
which is a non- rotating uncharged black
hole which is called a schwat trilled
black hole which is like almost
perfectly
spherical um you can construct that out
of anything you can take a bunch of
protons and neutrons and electrons dump
them into a region of space which is
smaller than the schwat radius of the
total mass and you have a black hole you
can take a bunch of neutrinos and do
that you can even take a bunch of
photons which are massless and create
and construct a black hole out of them
I'm talking about a gankin black hole a
thought experiment black hole I can use
paper and pen and take a bunch of
photons in my mind's eye and create a
system okay let's say I have a bunch of
photons it's a photon gas you you want
to know the properties the the the
statistical properties of a bunch of a
gas of photons look up Lando and LIF
shits one of the books and it will tell
you exactly what the properties are like
the temperature pressure all that of the
gas of photons you take a bunch of gas
of photons in a in in a spherical uh
container
which with with with perfectly
reflecting walls and you contract this
container
adiabatically and when it when the
container the radius of the container is
less than or equal to the short radius
of the gas of photons you have a black
hole so that's a thought experiment it's
a g experiment but I can construct a a
black hole using just photons with that
okay and that's the kind of mind games
you play when you when you're you know
doing research in quantum mechanics or
even studying quantum mechanics uh so a
black hole could be made of anything
essentially we don't know what's inside
the black hole that's the problem
there's an event horizon around the
black hole which is a boundary that is
completely opaque we don't know what's
inside you can throw anything into it
you can throw pizza into it you can
throw spaghetti into it you can throw a
car into it you can throw photons you
can throw whatever into it
antimatter and you won't know what
happened to the matter the material once
it crossed the boundary so from outside
a black hole has like they say no hair
it is known by only three parameters
Mass charge and angular momentum that's
it and for a swashi black hole it
doesn't have charge it doesn't have
angular momentum spin it only has
mass uh so we don't know what's inside
but if you are playing the thought
experiment game then you can construct a
black hole from the inside out and as
long as that black hole you're
constructing uh in your thought
experiment is not a micro black hole
with Quantum properties it's a large
black hole with classical properties
then you can play around with it and get
good results so for example uh this the
the radius of the Sun is about 0.7
million kilometers so the sun has a
diameter of about 1.4 or so million
kilometers the black hole at the center
of our galaxy The Milky Way
galaxy there's a black hole at its
center it's a super massive black hole
it has a few million solar masses it's
called Sagittarius AAR now that black
hole has a radius of about 14 million
kilometers okay that's about 20 times
the radius of the Sun that's how
gigantic that black black hole is it's a
very cold black hole and it's a
classical object it's not a Quantum
object so if you want to create that
sort of black hole through your through
your thought experiment then you can
construct it out of pizza you can cons
it out of cheese you can con it out of
anything you want um but as far as as we
know because of the limitations of
general relativity and because we don't
have a quantum theory of gravity we
don't quite know what what's inside the
black hole and what the internal
structure is like and therefore we don't
know what it's made of it could be made
of a bunch of strings or it may made of
of a bunch of fuzz balls or whatever
yeah and is it really a hole in in the
fabric of SpaceTime well it's not really
a hole okay it's not a hole it's not
like a hole would be like a worm hole in
Einstein Rosen Bridge that's not what a
black hole is it's just called a black
hole it's not even black actually it's
transparent it's
transparent and uh it it distorts the
fabric of SpaceTime because of its
gravitational effects on SpaceTime is it
solid I would I kind of you know I've
always visualized a black hole as as a
drop of liquid I don't see it as a solid
object I've always thought of a black
hole ever since I've been playing with
black holes I've always thought of black
holes as as as drops of fluid as
containers of
fluid some kind of fluid so I don't
think black holes are solid just like
the sun isn't a solid object is it the
sun isn't solid uh the sun's density is
is greater than that of water so the sun
is like a drop of fluid in a in a sense
so black holes also I I think of them as
drops of fluid they certainly aren
cannot be considered to be solid objects
as such I don't think anybody any any
physicist would think of black holes as
solid objects I I have I've always
thought I mean I haven't thought about
this for a while until I saw this
question I don't think I've always
thought of black holes as drops of some
kind of
fluid a different kind of fluid not
water but denser incredibly different
fluid but fluid
drops
okay okay sanskritic Yash says we know
that red shifting occurs when a light
source and observer move away from each
other or maybe the Observer is just
where he is or she is and the light
source is moving okay the Doppler effect
right red shift there's also evidence of
light that originated from the young
universe that's so red shifted that it
has now reached infrared wavelength so
is it possible for light to get so red
shifted that it reaches the wavelength
of radio waves multiple meters in length
also is there an upper limit to the
wavelength of light all right we're
talking about red shift so red shift is
is when you have a wave okay let's say a
wave of light and it gets stretched out
so that is red shift if it is blue
shifted it gets squeezed and its
frequency increases and wavelength
shortens uh so that's what happens now
how is light red shifted if you have the
source of light moving away from you or
if it is static and you moving away from
it then the waves the light waves see
appear to be red shifted okay they they
appear to be long have longer
wavelengths than what they had when they
originated from The Source that's a
standard Doppler effect Now red shift
can also happen because of the expansion
of the universe so the universe itself
is expanding and we don't quite know
what is footing the bill the energy bill
of the expansion of space time maybe the
energy is coming from the red shift
because it it's being taken out from the
photons that exist in the universe and
that's why they they are getting that's
one way of looking at it perhaps so uh
the photons the of the after glow of the
Big Bang the cosmic microwave background
radiation photons are tremendously red
shifted they are red shifted into the
millimeter wavelengths microwaves so yes
they are tremendously shifted uh and
some of them some of some part of of the
cmbr spectrum is definitely um in the in
has the wavelength of various kinds of
radio waves yes so it it certainly is
possible in the future as the universe
expands even more you will it will
eventually happen what will happen is
that the cmbr cosmic microwave backround
radiation it will eventually get R dread
shifted to wavelengths of multiple
meters tens of meters maybe kilometers
and it will be almost impossible or next
to impossible to detect them it will
happen yes so that is correct um so yes
it is possible for light to get so red
shifted it can reach the wavelength of
radio waves it can reach a wavelength of
multiple meters mul multiple kilometers
in length and there is no upper limit to
the wavelength of light I'll tell you
what's the upper limit of the wavelength
of light it's
infinity and when a wave and when a
light wave is red shifted to Infinity it
means it is red shifted out of
existence and that can happen when Right
light you don't
need I mean it can happen when when a
photon of light or a wave of light
comes in the path of a black
Hole uh and if if it did if
it so a black hole is a center and and
and Event Horizon and the closer your
your light wave comes to a black hole
the more red shifted it gets okay
because that's okay I'll not get into
how it happens the mechanism but it gets
red shifted you know the effect of
gravity on light the bending of light
and all that and there's a quantum
mechanical effect in that as well but if
the for phon touches the Event Horizon
tangentially it gets red shifted out of
existence which means that its
wavelength becomes Infinity so that is
the ultimate upper wave upper limit to
the wavelength of light Infinity which
means that the photon gets red shifted
out of existence it ceases to
exist okay adiya says why does a moving
charge produce magnetic
field why does a moving charge produce a
magnetic field now how do I explain this
I could explain it the physics way but I
could explain it a different way as well
so imagine um imagine you're standing
okay just standing and you are holding a
water balloon in your hands a balloon
filled with water and you're just
standing still so when you're standing
still the water inside that balloon is
just sitting there now think of this
water inside the
balloon to be like an electric charge at
rest because you're not moving you're
not running you standing still so this
water inside the balloon think of it as
an electric charge and it is not moving
it is at
rest okay now let's say you start
walking with the water balloon in your
hand you start walking I'm walking I'm
walking and have the balloon in my hand
so as I walk slowly the water inside the
balloon SLO es around a little bit okay
soses so this sloshing is like what
happens when an electric charge moves
and in the world of physics when an
electric charge moves it creates a
special kind of sloshing in the space
around it and we call this sloshing a
magnetic field now I was walking and
there's a little bit of sloshing right
now let's say start jogging I'm jogging
now so there is more sloshing the
sloshing is more vigorous and then let's
see I start sprinting at the highest
possible speed and then there's a
tremendous amount of sloshing that's
going on inside this balloon So the
faster the charge moves the stronger
this magnetic field becomes just like
how running faster makes the water
inside the balloon slos more and more
vigorously okay so that is kind of how a
magnetic field is produced when an
electric charge is in motion and this
magnetic field circles around the path
of the moving charge kind of how the
water might slash around swirl around in
a circular motion inside the balloon as
I'm running so whenever you see whenever
there is electricity flowing through a
wire which is just a bunch of moving
charges You'll Always Find that there's
a magnetic field that's created by this
process and that magnetic field is
surrounding the wire so a moving charge
produces this magnetic field now let me
get get into the physics of it very
basic the your moving charge produces a
magnetic field because of the
fundamental connection between
electricity and magnetism in nature and
also and and this phenomenon is actually
explained by special relativity and
electromagnetism so what happens is that
when a charge moves its electric field
appears different to a stationary
Observer because of relativistic effects
special relativity I'm not about general
relativity here so you you have moving
charge and its electric field appears
different to a stationary static
Observer because of special relativistic
effects and this relative motion causes
the electric field to be perceived
partly as a magnetic field by the
special by the stationary Observer and
the this resulting magnetic field that
is observed by the stationary Observer
it forms circular loops around the
direction of the motion of the charge
and the strength of this magnetic field
depends on the velocity of the charge
and the strength of its electric field
so the basis of of a
electromagnetism and the basis for the
production of a magnetic field by a
moving charge is special relativity and
this this explains why electric currents
which are moving charges generate
magnetic fields around wires
okay all
right next question is by
Rohan what is the relation between the
cosmological constant which Einstein
said was his biggest mistake and dark
energy on and dark matter so first of
all there's no relationship between the
cosmological constant and dark matter it
has some but it has something to do or
maybe a lot to do with dark
energy so these are closely related
Concepts in cosmology first of all what
is this cosmological constant this
cosmological
constant was originally introduced by
Albert Einstein in his field equations
in the Einstein field equations of
general relativity and he introduced
this constant to allow for a static
Universe because he he imagined that the
Universe should be static it should not
be expanding or Contracting it should be
static because in the 1910s and 1920s
the entire world believed that the
universe is a static Universe it's not
expanding or Contracting or anything
it's static so Einstein in produced this
cosmological constant in his field
equations to to allow for a static
Universe okay and this cosmological
constant this term represents a constant
energy density that permeates all of
space so that is what the cosmological
constant is now what is dark energy so
dark energy is a hypothetical form of
energy that's believed to be responsible
for the accelerating expansion of the
universe we discovered the that the
universe is EXP we know that the
universe is expanding but in the '90s I
believe 1990s we discovered that the
expansion of the universe is
accelerating okay somewhere around that
time and then this this dark energy had
this hypothetical form of energy which
is now called Dark Energy had to be
proposed which is believed to be
responsible for this accelerating
expansion of the universe so that is
cosmological concern that's dark energy
and now the what's the relationship so
now the cosmological constant is often
interpreted as a form of dark energy in
modern cosmology the cosmological
constant is considered to be the
simplest mathematical model that
explains Dark Energy so Einstein had
initially added this term the
cosmological constant to his equations
to create a static Universe static
Universe model because the prevailing
view at the time was that the Universe
was static
unchanging but in the 1920s 1930s Edwin
Hubble discovered that the universe is
expanding and this made Einstein's
static Universe model and the need for
the cosmological constant it made that
unnecessary and Einstein then removed
the cosmological constant from his
equations and he is reported to have
said that that was his biggest blunder
introducing the cosmological constant in
the equations was his biggest blunder so
Einstein regretted not trusting his
original equations which naturally
allowed for an expanding universe but
now that the we have discovered that the
expansion of the universe is
accelerating that this discovery led to
the Revival of the cosmological constant
this concept uh as a potential
explanation for Dark Energy so
Einstein's mistake is now seen as a very
preent addition that anticipated the
need to explain The Accelerated
expansion of the universe so the con the
the term that he had introduced for a
specific reason he then removed it and
now it is back and it seems to have a
different purpose and and a completely
different uh uh role to play but that's
what it is so that that is the
relationship between the cosmological
constant and uh Dark Energy but not dark
matter trendy Clips say is making a
super collider really worth it can it
lead to a disaster like nuclear power
plants well super colliders aren't
dangerous the way nuclear power plants
can potentially be dangerous I mean
we've had some accidents in the past
when it comes to nuclear power plants
we've had the Seven Mile Island uh
accident in the United States uh we had
the chernobil disaster which probably is
the worst accident nuclear accident till
date then you had Fukushima because of
the uh 19 because of the 2011 earthquake
and so on there may have been other such
other smaller instances as well
accidents as well so there is a certain
uh possibility or probability of of
nuclear radiation leaking out or
whatever in a nuclear
reactor and as long as the right
precautions are taken nothing happens
hopefully now when it comes to uh
colliders or super colliders there's no
nuclear radiation involved in these
colliders are simply gigantic vacuum
tubes with tremendously strong magnets
around them that accelerate
particles uh to almost the speed of
light and then they accelerate two beams
of particles in different directions
opposite directions and eventually
Collide them in a collision chamber with
a whole array of instruments around them
and then you want to see what comes out
of the debris of the Collision the the
gigantic Smash Up and hopefully you
discover new particles
because the energy of the two beams is
so incredibly high that the that it may
end up creating particles that we
haven't discovered or observed before so
that's what a super collider does and
there is no uh danger of it creating
some kind of nuclear uh accident because
there's no nuclear radiation involved at
all one of the dangers that people spoke
about before the LHC became operational
I remember in the 1990s I written I had
written not artical about this defending
the LHC so there was this uh group of
scientists who was petitioning that the
LHC should not be made operational
because
um because there was a view that that um
the at the time the possibility was
being explored that the LHC would be
able to create mini black
holes maybe one per second one mini
black hole per second micro black hole
per second uh in because of because of
the collisions and then the danger was
that what if these black Hool start
absorbing they they touch the walls of
of the of the collider and this the just
gobble up the Earth and the Earth would
seize to exist that was a danger right
and I remember in what 1910 what not 19
I'm sorry I'm not that old 2010 or
something 20 2008 2009 or something I
had WR written an article about this and
I demonstrated that it is impossible for
that to happen I'll not get into that
now the let's come to the question okay
so is making a super collider really
worth it so super
collider what you call a super collider
has to be something that has a greater
energy of its beams of it Collision
beams of the colliding particles than
the LHC maybe an order of I don't know
10 100 more times more or something like
that uh so why would you do it so let's
EX examine the pros and cons of creating
a super collider so if you have a super
collider which is way more powerful than
the large hydron collider then you can
explore higher energy scales a more
powerful collider can probe higher
energy scales which can potentially
discover new particles or or new
phenomena beyond the standard model and
that is what we hope for you know we
have a standard model but we want to
discover we want to go beyond that so a
super collor could potentially
possibly discover new particles in
phenomena and it even if it doesn't
Discover new phenomena or new particles
it will definitely provide more precise
measurements of known particles and
known interactions including the newly
discovered hibon it's still newly
discovered right um so even if nothing
new is discovered it will definitely
give us more precise measurements of
known particles and interactions and it
will help us understand the higs boson
and other such particles better and
obviously if you develop such a machine
it will lead to various kinds of
Innovations in accelerated technology
superc conducting magnets detector
systems and so on so forth so
technological and Engineering
advancements which is not something that
you really want you want actually you
actually want if you're building a super
collider you want to make fundamental
progress in physics and fundamental
discoveries new discoveries so these are
the pros of creating of of building a
super collider what are the drawbacks
what are the cons
so the most obvious con is the cost so
the large hydron collider is probably
the most expensive instrument or machine
ever built and building a new more
powerful collider would be incredibly
expensive extremely expensive and that
ex that expenditure will definitely
divert resources away from other
scientific Endeavors so that's that's a
big drawback then secondly there's no
guarantee that this new collider would
make any groundbreaking discoveries
because we have no idea we don't know
for certain what exists at higher energy
scales we just probing in the dark like
like blind like blind people we have no
idea what exists at higher energy scale
so there is absolutely no guarantee that
this new collider will make any kind of
ground baking discoveries I me the large
hydron collider was supposed to discover
all kinds of things super symmetric
particles and whatnot micro black holes
nothing the only new thing it discovered
was the higs boson nothing else so from
that perspective it's it's been kind of
uh disappointing okay so there's that so
there's no guarantee of any new
discovery and then your new collider
will
require tremendous amounts of energy to
operate the large hydron collider it
it's its energy bill is I think equal to
that of a small country okay just one
instrument imagine you have a super LC
or a super collider it's going to be the
energy equivalent of of a mediumsized
country perhaps imagine that right so
where does that energy come from you're
going to have to provide more energy you
know generate more energy how do you
generate more energy Europe is already
facing an energy crunch what you going
to do you're going to burn Cal they
already shutting down the nuclear
reactors in Germany and what wherever
else so there's Environmental concerns
and all that if you have to burn coal to
do that or then or maybe you have to get
the energy by burning gas and you get it
from Russia that is taboo right now and
we'll not talk about geopolitics right
now but there you have it right and so
on so overall I would say that because
there is no guarantee of any new
discovery and because of the incredible
costs involved in in building the
collider and then operating the collider
overall I think it's not a great
idea I if you have that much money to
throw around why not fund other
experiments and fund other research you
know there's so much research that needs
to be done in so many different fields
so I I would say you'd rather I would if
if I were to make the decision if I had
the funding I would not build a new
collider I would maybe build a few
telescopes on the moon or I would I
would fund other scientific research
there's so much more that needs to be
funded so that's that's how I see it
yaja
9449 says what happens if someone
crosses through the center of the
so-called ring lity the ring shaped
Singularity of zero thickness at the
center of a spinning charged black hole
such that the crossing happens
perpendicular to the plane of the rular
without touching it in other words what
happens if we enter a spinning charged
black hole along the axis of rotation of
the black hole so what is saying or she
is saying I'm not sure who it is okay
let's say you have a so you're talking
about a black hole that has mass it has
charge it has angular momentum which is
spin so it is spinning just like the
Earth spins around its axis the north
south axis okay that's the axis of
rotation and we are going to enter the
this black hole along the axis of
rotation the north south axis maybe
along the north pole or the South Pole
that's what we talking about and that's
what the question is about so first of
all let's understand what kind of black
hole we talking about when How many
kinds of black holes exist so the
simplest black hole we can think of is a
black hole that has mass it has no
charge it has no spin or angular
momentum okay so this is called a
Schwartz black hole it has a completely
spherical Event Horizon then you have a
black hole that has mass it is spinning
which means it has angular momentum but
it doesn't have any charge so such a
black hole is called a curve black hole
k r r it has mass it has angular
momentum spin it has an oblate squashed
Event Horizon and it has an ergosphere
which is a region outside the Event
Horizon where objects cannot remain
stationary that's a cur black hole then
you have black holes that have mass and
charge but are not spinning let's a rner
no th black hole okay so these black
holes are mass and charge they have two
spherical Horizons there is the Event
Horizon outside and there's a CI Horizon
inside and inside the Cy Horizon weird
stuff happens okay and then you have a
black hole with mass charge angular
momentum that's a curv Newman black hole
it has mass charge spin it has a complex
structure with an erosphere and multiple
Horizons an event horizon and a Ki
Horizon and now the black hole we're
talking about is the Cur Numan black ho
and it has a singularity which is not a
point Singularity it's a ring
Singularity it's called you could call
it ring ority okay uh so this is the Cur
new man black hole that we talking about
now so if somebody were to
enter were to cross through the center
of the spinning charged black hole along
the axis of rotation then you if you
were to enter through there you would
experience some very strange effects
because of the extreme warping of space
time but you may not necessarily be
destroyed immediately because if you go
through the axis of rotation you will
avoid the ring ority the ring shaped
Singularity okay you'll go you you
you'll go through it but you will not
touch the singularity you'll not touch
the ring you'll just go through it so uh
so you will avoid direct contact with
this rular you're going to cross the
outer Event Horizon and you may not
perceive anything if the black hole is
large enough you may not even know that
you've crossed the Event Horizon then
you will uh go inside you'll continue
inside and then you will pass through
the inner Horizon which is called The
kosi Horizon C Au U CH h y kosi Horizon
and once you pass through the kosi
Horizon you enter a region where
conventional physics breaks down and you
no longer know what's going to happen
Okay so over here in this in this region
causality breaks down or causality
becomes confusing and you may end up
seeing multiple versions of the universe
you may even end up seeing your own
past so that's what happens when you go
past the The kosi
Horizon and once you cross the outer
Horizon the The Event Horizon you can no
longer communicate with the outside
universe and so
on uh so inside the Ki Horizon
everything goes strange and
uh and the causality breaks down but you
are going to if you if you go through
the axis along the axis you're going to
bypass the singularity you will avoid
the regularity but you may end up
getting spaghettified so you will
definitely depending on the size of the
black hole and the size of the rular you
will experience tidal forces if the
regularity is small and not too large
you may experience extreme tidal Force
and extreme electromagnetic effects
because of the charged nature of black
hole and you may get stretched out into
very long strands of spaghetti
spaghettification and it's even possible
that the region inside the inner Horizon
inside the Kia Horizon uh may have
negative energy states so you may um you
may experience extremely strange bizarre
effects you may see multiple versions of
the universe you may encounter white
hole like phenomena you may even exit
the black hole into another universe or
maybe another part of the universe which
is the uh Wormhole situation and all so
this is all highly speculative okay we
we we don't exactly know what will
happen but we know that causality breaks
down down here inside inside the kosi
Horizon and Quantum gravitational
effects also become important near the
singularity but we don't have a theory
of quantum gravity that explains what
happens so essentially this is is
something that we don't quite understand
because of the limitations of known
physics while crossing the center of the
spinning charge black hole along the
axis of rotation you will definitely
theoretically avoid the ring ority but
you're going to pass through regions of
SpaceTime where our current
understanding of physics breaks down and
the actual experience will probably be
Stranger Than science
fiction that's what I could say
okay once again by yala is it possible
that we may be living in a false vacuum
which is metast stable but is not in its
most stable state if that is so is it
true that such a false vacuum can Decay
any time such that the influence of the
Decay happens with the vacuum speed of
light and thus we may not be able to
even detect the DC even in principle if
the false vacuum decays it would like
mean the end of all matter in the
universe after the DC of the false
vacuum happens wouldn't it okay what do
we mean by vacuum dek what are we
talking about what what is a vacuum what
is a false vacuum we have to understand
this first right what is a false vacuum
what do we mean by that what do we mean
by by by the statement that the universe
is in maybe a false vacuum or a true
vacuum we talking about the higs bone
and the higs field here first of all
understand that this has everything to
do about with the higs
field uh
so we've all heard of the higs bosone
right the it is completely incorrectly
called the God particle there's no it's
not a supernatural thing it's it's it's
journalists who have given this term to
this higs boson but the higs boson is
this is is a particle that endows the
Universe and the particles in the
universe with mass and the more strongly
fundamental particle inter acts with the
higs field the more massive it is and
the less and and the less strongly a
particle interacts with the higs field
the less massive it is and some
particles simply don't interact with the
Hig field which is why particles like
the like the photon are massless okay so
the Hig boson Has a Field corresponding
to it which is the higs field and this
Hig field permeates the entire universe
according to Quantum field Theory and so
on so this Hig field is a scal field
that exists in a vacuum and what's a
scalar field what's a vector field
what's what's scalar versus Vector a
scalar quantity is a physical quantity
with only magnitudes but it has no
Direction so mass is a scalar field
electric charge is a scalar field is is
is a scalar quantity and so on and
Vector quantities are physical
quantities that have magnitude as well
as Direction Force weight Etc so the
higs field is a scalar field
okay and the higs field has potential
energy now let's take a look at what the
higs field looks looks like because the
higs field has the shape of a Mexican
hat the higs potential higs
field let me let me uh put that on the
screen higs
field higs
potential so it has the shape of a
Mexican hat so to say okay kind of you
see that
that's what the field uh is shaped like
now you can see it has a hill and it has
a it has at least one Valley maybe
multiple valleys and so on
right uh so so that's what the higs
field is it has the shape of a Mexican
hat now there is there could be multiple
ground states of the higs field and the
ground state or the ground state means
the most stable State and the ground
state of the
universe depends on the potential of the
higs field that permeates the vacuum of
the universe so
uh as you can see over here you have two
uh ground States one one is a false you
know a metast stable ground state a
higher ground state and one is a lower
ground state which means U so so if the
universe is in
um let's say uh
so there's a there's a local minimum and
a global
minimum and the local minimum if it is
it is more
energetic than the global minimum then
then the universe may be in a metast
stable uh vacuum in a local vacuum so
what do we mean by all this is what we
have to understand but but you can see
here stable meta stable all that so if
the universe lies in a global minimum in
the global minimum of the higs potential
which is the true vacuum State then it
is stable but if the
minimum of is is local and there is
another minimum which is deeper than
that then the vacuum is false and the
universe is metast
stable so uh let us see
here this is an example with
the I think this is a better
representation can I find a better
image let us
quickly look here maybe
this okay let's take this as the thing
okay so maybe we are at this point which
is meta stable but there could be a uh a
global minimum that is that is deeper
that is deeper and different so if we
are in a false vacuum a metast stable
vacuum then then the universe is metast
stable and what might happen is that our
universe might tunnel out of where we
are into the true vacuum State via a
process called Quantum tunneling so in
quantum theory a stable or true vacuum
corresponds to the global minimum of the
scalar potential which is the higs
potential and a metastable or false
vacuum it is instead a local minimum not
a global minimum and if our universe
lies in the only minimum of the higs
potential then we are fine or if the
universe lies in the deepest minimum of
the Hig potential then we are fine but
if we lie in a local minimum and a
deeper minimum exists then uh the
universe will eventually via Quantum
tunneling
uh tunnel into the other state into the
true vacuum and if that happens then
everything that we know of will be
destroyed so this process of quantum
tunneling is unpredictable okay Quantum
tunneling is is well known in quantum
mechanics students study that uh so
Quantum tunneling is unpredictable it
can happen completely spontaneously and
if the universe is in a false vacuum of
the higs potential of the higs field it
could potentially Decay tunnel to a
lower energy State at any time it could
happen spontaneously for example we know
there are quantum fluctuations in the
universe Quantum fluctuations could
potentially cause a small region of
space in the universe to Tunnel through
the energy barrier and transition to the
true vacuum state of the higs potential
of the Hig field and this would create a
bubble a small bubble of true vacuum
that would then expand outwards at the
speed of life light so this DEC would
spread at the speed of light creating a
bubble an ever expanding Bubble at the
speed of light of true vacuum that
expands outward so you are correct that
we may not be able to detect this DK
before it reaches us because it is
traveling at the speed of light and no
information can travel faster than the
speed of light and this decay of a false
vacuum would have catastrophic
consequences for the universe as we know
it so as this bubble of true vacuum
expands it would fundamentally alter the
laws of physics and all the properties
of matter within it so this would
definitely lead to the end of all matter
as we know it in the affected regions
matter will once this happens matter
will have very different properties than
what we know
so that definitely means the end of all
life if if this this reaches the Earth
so that's what this is and of course of
course the probability of such a such
such a thing such a catastrophic event
happening is extremely small because we
know the universe has remained in its
present state for at least about 13.8
billion years so this concept of false
vacuum is definitely well established in
theoretical physics but we have
absolutely no experimental evidence that
our universe is in a false vacuum state
but the even this the smallest
probability smallest possibility of an
of such such an end of the world that
could happen obviously is is is scary
it's
disquieting and if it happens it's
definitely going to be the end of the
universe as we know it and definitely
the end of life as you know it but I
suppose we won't even notice if it
happens we won't have time to realize
what's happening it'll just happened in
an
instant and a third question by
vka does the top Quark Decay before it
gets affected by color confinement and
thus can a bare top Quark be observed in
general can be quarks be observed above
the Hagedorn temperature okay we have a
number of Concepts over here that we
have to speak about one is uh the
Hagedorn temperature so what is this
Hagedorn temperature so the Hagedorn
temperature is a theoretical temperature
limit in particle physics in the context
of what we call hydronic matter what is
hydronic matter hydronic matter is your
standard matter that you are aware of
matter that is made of
quarks so protons and neutrons are made
of quarks electrons aren't made of
quarks okay electrons aren't hyrons
they're
Leons but the universe that we know the
world that we know is all hydronic
matter and the Hagedorn temperature is a
theoretical temperature limit in the
context of hydronic matter so at this
temperature the hagedon temperature if
you add more energy to a system of
particles like let's say you have
particle accelerator or you have the
early universe and you add more energy
to a system of particles at this
temperature then this doesn't increase
the temperature it instead produces more
particles okay so the idea is that at
very high temperatures the energy
density is so high that it continuously
converts into the creation of new Artic
new particles so the hagedon temperature
is a theoretical upper limit on the
temperature of matter Beyond which our
current understanding of particle
physics breaks down and this is
essentially represents a phase
transition between different phases of
matter like between water and ice or
water and steam these are different
phases of of of water right similarly
the hagon temperature represents a phase
transition
um temperature and uh it's it's about
1.75 trillion Kelvin 1.7 * 10 12 Kelvin
that's the Hagedorn
temperature that is what it is now we're
talking about bare quarks right so at
temperatures above the hagedon
temperature there will be a phase
transition and there will be a different
state of matter that will exist and that
M phase of matter state of matter is
called a quark gluon Plasma in a quark
gluon plasma quarks and gluons
deconfined and they can move freely it's
a soup of qux and gluons gluons are are
Force carriers so to say okay so they
will all intermingle they will be
deconfined and they they'll move around
freely it will be qu Quark glow and soup
Quark GL plasma and this state of matter
could potentially allow for the
observation of what you call bare quarks
okay now what is color confinement
that's another term that we are using
over here color confinement so color
confinement states that quarks cannot be
isolated singularly quarks can only be
found in Bound States called hron okay
so there are six quarks up down top
bottom strange charm and these are the
fundamental building blocks of the of of
hydronic
matter um so so confinement says that
you cannot have isolated quarks quarks
are always found in Bound States called
hyrons now there is something called
color charge
okay and think of it as a Quantum
property it's not really a charge and
it's not really colors like red blue red
green and blue even though quarks carry
what we call one of the three color
charges red green and blue but this
color charge is actually some a kind of
quantum property so quarks carry one of
three color charges red green blue and
anti- quarks carry anti- colors anti-
red red anti- green anti- blue and there
is a property called color neutrality so
hyrons bound states of quarks are always
color neutral so this can be achieved by
either combining three quarks with
different colors into Barons okay
protons and neutrons are Barons and they
are made made of three quarks or you can
combine a quark and an antiquark with
corresponding color and anti-color
charge which are maons pons chons Etc
okay so that's how you achieve color
neutrality so similar to how atom are
electrically neutral because they have
equal numbers of protons and electrons
similarly hyrons are color neutral
because their quar colors combin to
cancel each other out now there is a
strong force involved in Quark
interactions and the strong force
between quarks increases with distance
okay in electromagnetism in the
gravitational force when two objects or
two bodies move away from each other the
force decreases with distance right with
increasing distance the force decreases
one upon r but in quarks the strong
force between quarks increases with
difference so imagine two quarks there
are connected by a rubber band a flux
tube so if you pull them apart you're
going to have to you know impart a
tremendous amount of energy and as you
pull them apart the tension in this band
this rubber band that connects the two
quarks increases increases increases
until the band
snaps and when the band snaps it creates
two new ends and this snapping
essentially represents the creation of a
new Quark antiquark
pair this leads to the formation of two
new hrones instead of isolating two
single quarks so that's essentially what
it is okay that that is
U color confinement and all that now
above the hagador temperature the
concept of confinement color confinement
no longer applies and the thermal energy
is sufficient to overcome the strong
force the thermal energy of the
temperature is sufficient to to to
overcome this strong force that confines
quarks within hydrons and that's how you
the formation of the Quark gluon plasma
where quarks and gluons freely move
around over large distances and this
state of matter is believed to have
existed just after the big bag now you
are mentioning the top Quark it is the
heaviest of the quarks it is an
extremely massive Quark it's Unique
among all the quarks because it is
tremendously massive it decays extremely
quickly and it decays faster than and
the time it would take for color
confinement which is the process that
binds quarks together to form hron okay
so pop
quarks uh are unique such that in such a
way that it is possible to observe an
unconfined bare top Quark in
experiments and that is about
it okay Rohan says the following is a
quote from Brian Green's book until the
end of time it's only by comparison that
with the demonstrably incorrect
classical view the view we humans
discovered first because it's both
simpler and extraordinarily accurate on
the scales accessible to human senses
that Quantum reality seems hazy it's
actually the classical perspective that
provides an approximate and hence
imprecise view of the two of the true
Quantum reality what are my views on
this are we classical beings living in a
Quantum world
well the world definitely emerges from
the quantum domain from the Ultram
microscopic scale and all the processes
all the phenomena all the phenomena
whatever we see uh originates from
quantum mechanics I mean if you see
light light is a quantum mechanical
phenomenon the very fact that matter
occupies space comes from Po's Exclusion
Principle which is a quantum mechanical
principle
everything that we experience has a
quantum mechanical origin for sure so we
inhabit a world that we
perceive such that it doesn't have any
quantum mechanical phenomena except for
certain objects like crystals Etc whose
properties are entirely quantum
mechanical but most of the things that
we experience are non-quantum phenomena
and these are what we call the classical
phenomena so we the world we we
experience is is a classical world
and quantum mechanics obviously is
extremely
complicated it it involves an extremely
small extremely small scales which we
can't
perceive um So that obviously is the
true world but the world we observe is
also the true world and our brains our
minds aren't that powerful that we could
perceive Quantum phenomena and and and
process them in real time because that
is so complicated imagine you have got a
phone okay you've got a phone here and
you see stuff on the screen and if you
but inside the phone you have voltages
and you have Gates and you have all
kinds of circuits and you've got
billions and billions of millions maybe
billions of of circuits on the Silicon
wafer and if you want to send an email
you to toggle all kinds of voltages and
do whatnot you think you can do it
cognitively in real time you can't so
what what the phone interface shows you
is a very very high level abstraction of
what of the complexity that happens
inside and that's kind of how we see the
world because our brains aren't that
complicated so uh the classical world is
obviously the true world but the quantum
world is also the true world so there
these are different representation of
the world this these are different ways
in which we can think of the world
interpret the world and uh that's just
what it is so we are classical beings
but we emerge from the quantum
uh from the quantum
scale our thoughts I don't know where
they emerge from our our our
Consciousness I don't know what where
that comes from we still don't know but
yeah but I wouldn't say that the
classical view is
incorrect U it is correct to a
certain um degree of
correctness you know it it depends up to
which decimal point you want it to be
correct that's just how it is
ADI S1 says recently you tweeted about
encouraging learning physics all over
again from scratch so I need advice on
that please suggest how to approach
physics from scratch as I'm already in
my undergraduate level now oh so I
remember a few days ago somebody had
said that he or she wants to relearn
physics a priority from scratch and I I
kind of just encouraged that person yeah
that I approve of it uh but how would
one do that so look I was talking about
learning physics from scratch all over
again like learning for the sake of
actually learning with the objective of
maybe doing actual research in physics
if you are in the at the undergraduate
level then you need to get your degrees
and all that which means you have to
pass exams so learning physics for the
for the purpose of passing exams is
extremely different from learning
physics for the sake of doing research
in physics very very different
approaches are required when it comes to
passing exams you have to be very
ruthless very practical
you
to take shortcuts you know shortcuts are
your best friend you to memorize lots of
equations and formula just just mug it
up and you could to solve lots of
problems and in in the Indian context
you to learn how to write like 50 page
essays for some some mundane topic and
10 such say you would write in one exam
in a matter of three hours so it depends
on which exam which academic system and
so on so my I I I am not great at giving
advice about how to learn physics for
the purpose of passing exams I'm you
know that's never something that has
interested me I can give you advice
about how to genuinely learn physics a
priority from scratch if you want to do
research in physics in in whatever field
interests you so I would say if you want
to go back to the basics and learn
physics from scratch and at the end of
the process you want to do you want to
be able to do actual research at the
highest level it would take you five
years roughly roughly give or take and
if I were to do that I would spend at
least two years just doing basic math go
back to your high school or college
level mathematics do relearn algebra Le
yeah why not relearn algebra do all the
sh series books just chew them up do all
the do all the problems relearn calculus
differential equations um
uh uh what else do we have in quantum
mechanics uh linear algebra
matrices all of that learn all of that
then go through the books of uh
mathematical methods for physics at two
different levels one would be Mary Mary
boss the other would
be
uh what is that I I have the book behind
me so there there's at least two books
you need to do and then once you're done
with all of that and you're really
really solid with math because when you
start solving problems in the
mathematical methods for methods for
physics
books uh then you're already doing
physics even if you take a proper course
a textbook thick textbook on
differential equations you doing physics
right there whether you know it or not
so once you're done with the mathematics
you solved all the problems then you
start then you spend one year at least
doing your classical physics uh which is
Newtonian mechanics maybe uh definitely
newon Newton mechanics electromagnetism
M and
uh statistical physics statistical
mechanics all that then you move on to
quantum mechanics and relativity and
then you would spend some time solving
hundreds of problems in quantum
mechanics you start with griffits then
you go to zti and then you go to
shanker's level and eventually Lando and
lifshits uh and then you obviously have
to uh do learn tensor calculus and you
have to do at least a couple of books on
relativity it's a it's a long long climb
ahead but if you go through this entire
process which may take you five years
you're going to be solidly equipped for
doing actual research in physics that's
how I would do it if you're in your
undergraduate level and you have to pass
exams I would not Advocate this approach
take your shortcuts do your memorization
you're mugging up solve as many problems
possible ideally just take the past 10
years exam papers and solve them over
and over again that's what you would do
that's that's how you would do very well
in your exams you'll get your degree but
I'm not sure how well you will learn
physics uh by doing
this so my point is in life you have to
be practical you cannot be idealistic if
you're a student you have to get get
your godamn degree you're going to get
good marks so be practical be ruthless
do what's required then you can see then
if you want you can learn actual physics
and you can do you can follow the
guidelines the P the outline I just laid
out for that which may take you five
years but physics is is is a extremely
vast field and there's so much to learn
in that it takes time and the
entire basis of physics is mathematics
you have to be good at mathematics at
least you need to be good at learning
math okay there's something there's a
problem I need to solve how do I solve
it oh yeah I need this piece of math so
let me learn it in the next two three
days so you should be able to quickly
learn new math if required maybe you
need to learn group Theory maybe galwa
groups or whatever or whatever you know
I mean Einstein had to learn
tensors just so that he could invent he
could you know formulate the equations
of general relativity and he hated math
he was not good at math Heisenberg did
not know what a commutator
was okay uh when when he ran into his
uncertainty principle on an island
called helgoland so he didn't know what
commutators were he did not know what
matrices were when he formulated Matrix
mechanics and so on so you as a
theoretical physicist you have to be
able to quickly pick up new math and
that's a skill you need to have all
right I'm done with all the questions
from the comments let's take some
questions from the live chat manasi says
mug up physics no you don't mug up
physics you mug up the formulas and the
equations and all the shortcuts for
passing exams but but if you want to do
real research you don't mug up anything
you you need to understand the concepts
and you have all the textbooks so you
need to just open the textbook and find
whatever you need to find for example I
was talking about a gas of photons what
are the properties of a gas of photons
what is what is the what is the equation
of State for a gas of
photons what is the uh the the the
representation of the temperature and
the pressure of a gas of gas of photons
what's the what's the entropy of a gas
of photons and so on so forth I don't
need to memorize that I would never do
that I'll just open Lando and lifshits
wherever it is the book on statistical
mechanics I think or whichever one it is
I got a whole bunch of them you find the
thing and then you take that and use it
so in the real world you don't need to
mug up stuff but for exams in India
especially in this stupid idiotic Indian
academic system you know mug UPS off
which is unfortunate
unfortunate
uh we're going to take questions about
physics and science today not about
mysticism and religion and history
astrology all that all right please ask
me questions about science today
tomorrow I will take questions about
everything
else okay okay let's take this Aram says
after jwsd James web Space Telescope
discovered galaxies which are expected
to be older
than excuse me what excuse
[Laughter]
me okay let me read the question after
the James web Space Telescope discovered
galaxies which are expected to be older
than the Big Bang should we now consider
that we have to revise the Big Bang
Theory once again okay let me explain
what's happened the James web Space
Telescope has discovered the oldest
galaxies that we have discovered thus
far and they are I assure you they're
not older than the Big Bang but they are
older than what we expected the first
galaxies to
be they're about 200 million years um
the the the first galaxies
emerged about 200 or so million years
after the big bang we expect that they
would the first galaxies would emerge
about a billion or so years after the
big bank so they are way too early they
formed way too early so that kind
of forces us now to revise our
understanding of how galaxies form so
that's what happened that's what's
happened we don't have to revise the Big
Bang Theory these galaxies aren't older
than the Big Bang nothing at all is
older than the big bag that is simply an
impossibility okay so we have discovered
the oldest galaxies ever and we kind of
don't know how come they are so old I
mean so so so old yes how did they how
did they form so quickly after the big
bang 200 or 230 or so million years
after the big bang which is ridiculous
which which is incredible so that is the
problem we facing it's a good problem to
have we always want as a physicist you
want to discover new things which kind
of upset everything upset and and and go
against the current understanding of
physics because that's where there's a
new problem to solve and physics is all
about solving new problems so you find
new data which represents a problem a
crisis and you a great now I have
something to do otherwise it's all
business as usual so that's what's
happened I'm glad this has happened that
jwst is throwing up new data which is is
kind of revising the way we look at the
universe and that's what's happened so
we don't have the answers yet but we I'm
sure we we will figure it out sooner or
later man is saying I'm saying for the
exams it's a royal subject a subject of
understanding of course of course for
the exams yes you have to mug up physics
for the exams I completely agree and
that's what I also say you have to be
practical and you should mug up physics
for the exams if you have
to um and once again Mani says what are
the current challenges in physics there
are so
many things that are not understood in
physics uh for example all the stuff
that the James web Space Telescope is
throwing up I mean that is challenging
our current understanding of
physics um how do black holes form how
how do super massive black holes form
and that's not related to jwst but
overall we don't know how super massive
black holes form uh they should take
very long time to form but even every
Galaxy seems to have one at the center
how does that happen what's dark matter
we don't know what dark matter is what
is dark energy we don't have the the the
least clue as to what dark energy is so
95% of the universe is dark now then
what are neutral oscillations where
where do they come from
um oh there's so much more why do we
have various
constants you know constant quantities
in
physics why why why why do they have
those quantities why do they have those
specific values various constants like
the uh like the uh gravitational
constant like the gravitational coupling
constant the electromagnetic magnetic
coupling constant various constants in
physics which seem to have completely
arbitrary values why do these values
exist why not other
values uh so so much more right why is
the universe expanding why is the
expansion accelerating what's the
ultimate face fate of the universe we're
going to have a big rip or we're going
to have a big crunch what is the true
nature of
gravity we don't understand gravity at
all we simply don't understand gravity
what is time my goodness what is time
where does it come from
is it an emergent property of the
universe do we have atoms and molecules
of time or is it something that comes
from outside the Universe I mean in
quantum mechanics time is a is an
external parameter it's a classical
parameter it's not a Quantum parameter
it doesn't emerge out of quantum
mechanics it is it comes into quantum
mechanics from outside so many open
problems in physics we understand next
to nothing of the universe okay so
there's challenges everywhere absolutely
everywhere what is
consciousness I mean it should have a
physical explanation should it
not are we living in a
simulation so much I mean that's why
physics is so fascinating because there
are so many open problems in
physics okay let's take questions from
other
people
uh Karan nwat says what is ether so
ether was there's no ether okay there's
no such thing as ether but there used to
be this uh this this belief in the past
until I think the late 19th century
maybe even the early 20th century that
there is something called The Ether uh
which which permeates
space and because we know that space is
a vacuum then how does light propagate
in space I mean waves need a medium to
propagate right how can waves propagate
without a medium waves need a medium
within which to propagate at so that's
why there has to be an ether out there
something called The Ether within which
light propagates that was the
belief and then there was a very famous
experiment called the Michaelson morle
experiment with the Michaelson morly
interferometer which is the basis for
the uh for Lio which is the
gravitational wave observator that we
have so the Michaelson morle experiment
conclusively proved that ether doesn't
exist okay so that is now an obsolete
concept and we know that ether doesn't
exist but it was this hypothetical uh
medium through which light could
propagate now we know that light doesn't
need a medium to Pro
propagate
okay
um uh ishant Singh says is everything
predestined according to
science uh super determinism isn't it
so look we know that the laws of physics
seem to be deterministic if you have a
ball and you drop it it's going to
follow the laws of physics so you have
an initial set set of initial conditions
the ball is at a certain altitude
certain height above the ground and I
drop it I let it go it has a certain
Mass it's going to fall towards the
ground it's going to bounce off it and
you can based on very simple equations
You can predict the entire path of the
ball all the way into the future and if
you can do that into the future you can
even do it in the into the past if you
know the all the parameters of of the
system that system includes me the
atmosphere the environment the
temperature the motion of the Earth the
motion of the Sun the motion of the sun
around the Milky Way the motion of the
Milky Way Around the around the local
super cluster and so on so forth all the
parameters if you know then you can
actually essentially predict the future
as well as the past so and it's all
differential equations so from that
perspective it looks like everything is
pretty
predetermined predestined and then you
have uncertainty because quantum
mechanics is not deterministic it is
probabilistic so you have Quantum
fluctuations which are entirely random
then you have the uncertainties in
quantum mechanics the Heisenberg
uncertainty principle so those that
introduces Randomness in the universe
through because of which you can't
predict everything but that Randomness
is also entirely random and and
uh so it's
it's so the question actually is the
real question over
here is do we have free
will if I'm choosing to snap my fingers
here right here is it because I have
decided to do it or is it because it was
just programmed into the initial
conditions of the universe that at this
point in time this being over here will
snap his fingers that's a real question
and we don't quite have the answers to
that or maybe we do and uh it is kind of
scary because if you look deep into this
it may actually end up telling you that
we don't have free will and everything
is pred predetermined
predestined but that's not how I see it
at least I choose not to see it that way
I I want to believe that I have
free all
right okay
um movies says is 2+ 2 equal 4 well as
far as I know it's it is 2 + 2 equals 4
now let's take some other
question so many questions I let me try
and take questions from someone has uh
not asked question thus
far I will not take questions about
history etc
etc okay Shri Watsa says if space itself
can expand faster than the speed of
light then why are gravitational waves
limited to travel at the speed of light
so gravitational
waves propagate within the fabric of
SpaceTime in SpaceTime itself expands
due to mysterious processes and it can
expand faster than than the speed of
light and if you have a gravitational
wave that's propagating within space Ty
while it is expanding the gravitational
wave will only expand will only travel
the speed of light that's just how it is
you know so yeah you can you know there
is a universal speed limit in the
universe which is the speed of light but
that applies to objects and processes
and phenomena that
travel within space time and occur
within the within the fabric of
SpaceTime but the fabric of SpaceTime
itself can expand at any speed it's like
having a
balloon you expand a balloon there's
there's an ant sitting on the balloon
okay on the surface of the balloon when
you expand it hard and the balloon
expands whoosh like that then the ant
may end up traveling from its
perspective faster than the speed of
light but it's actually not traveling it
is spacetime itself which is expanding
so that's how it is I know it's
counterintuitive but that's just the way
it is there is so much about relativity
and quantum mechanics that is not
intuitive at all it simply doesn't fit
in with the way we have always
experience the world because we live on
a planet which is traveling around the
Sun and in the environment that we live
in these phenomena don't happen
relativistic phenomena we don't
experience them ever such phenomena you
will experience them if you go near a
black hole or yeah where you have
extremes of energy density or mass
density or extreme velocities that's
where you can observe Rel relativistic
effects and we are not in such an
environment so it is completely
counterintuitive to whatever we imagine
but that's just the way it
is I will not take questions about
Tantra manra okay in in today's session
at
least
uh why do people ask questions about
other topics when this is a science
episode um
some questions I've taken many times but
okay let's see udit Narayan says is
there a center of the universe yes from
my perspective the center of the
universe is right here from your
perspective the center of the universe
is where you are it's
because uh the observable universe is
something that is centered around
you that's because uh look the
observable universe has a radius of
about
uh has a diameter of of about 95 billion
light years okay because of the
expansion of the universe and the center
of the observable universe is where you
are or where I am from my perspective
it's where I am from the your
perspective it's where you are and from
from our Collective perspective it's the
planet Earth because it's from here that
we looking around so it's the center of
the observable universe but this true
center of the universe we don't know
where it is we don't know how large the
universe is whether it is infinite
whether it is finite what what shape it
has we have no idea but we only can see
a certain partion portion of the
universe and from that perspective the
center is where we
are um OAS says there are so many
earthlike planets in their respective
Golden Ox zones could they also have
humans the scariest thing to find out in
find in outer space would be non
Earth humans well we know of multiple
planets by now that exist in their
respective Goldilocks zones of
their parent Stars the goldilock zone is
that is that specific
region around a star where the
temperature is such that you can have
liquid water so for our our star system
the Sun the goldilock Zone in the
goldilock zone we have three planets
Venus Earth and Mars
and depending on the size of the sun and
the temperature of the of the star and
all that you can have different sizes
and distances of the goldo zone and we
know of many planets exoplanets that
exist in their respective goldilock
zones so could they also have humans
look it's possible that there could be
life there it's also possible that could
there could be intelligent life there
could there be humanoid humanlike life
there that's also possible okay but we
haven't observed that we have never seen
it thus far the possibility is there I
mean there are 10 raised to see there is
at least 10 raised to 22 or 23 planets
in the observable universe that is one
with 22 zeros after
it and it's just a
probabilistic likely I mean it's almost
a certainty that life and intelligent
life would exist somewhere out there but
the universe is so large that we may
never be able to discover it or maybe if
you're lucky or maybe if you're unlucky
cover it so I I think it's possible that
there could be life intelligent life
maybe even human-like life or there and
yeah it would be scary perhaps to find
such life to discover such life and come
across
that
okay um what is escape velocity the
escape velocity for any object is that
velocity which will allow your rocket
your spacecraft to break free of the
gravitational pull of that object so for
the earth I believe the escape Velocity
is what 11 12 or something km/ second
for the Moon is much less much lesser
than that of the earth so so there's a
formula for escape velocity which you
can derive using basic neonian mechanics
um which you can look up and it's the
minimum velocity that your spacecraft or
your projectile needs to permanently
escape the gravity ational potential of
the planet or the star that it wants to
escape from that is escape velocity for
the earth I think it's about 11 or 12
kilometers per second for the sun it may
for the solar system it may be way more
maybe hundreds of kilometers per
second
uh okay do we have anything
else there's obviously lots of other
questions and uh
um Umar maheswari says according to
Quantum Mechanics is it true that when
there is no Observer there is no
observation then if we are not being
observed then do we theoretically not
exist well it's a good question right uh
imagine we all do a thought experiment
we humans we decide that at so and so
time tomorrow none of us will look at
the
Moon okay so everybody on the planet
Earth will not look at the Moon we'll
all look somewhere else will the moon
disappear then so this is kind of a
philosophical thought
experiment the observer effect doesn't
mean that actually the observer effect
means that uh the act of observing
something ends up modifying or changing
the thing that you're observing that's
what it means I gave a proper answer
just at the beginning of this episode
you can once the episode is over you can
go and check it out again so it doesn't
mean that okay so because you're not
observing or nobody's observing
something it doesn't mean it doesn't
exist it does exist but uh so the
Observer the observer effect doesn't
mean that the act of observation makes
something exist it means that the act of
observation changes that thing that
you're observing or measuring okay so
yeah I
mean you can think of it that way that
you know um for something to exist it
has to be observed
and that way and and you could then
argue that if if we exist then if if
somebody from outside has to observe
something for it to exist then who is
observing our
universe
yeah okay I think I will uh I will now
essentially take maybe one more question
I've taken Dyson spares lots of times I
have many Clips on this channel about
Dyson Sphere
om says that the higs boson was
discovered on today's date yes yes happy
birthday higs
boson and that's about
it um kishan bolker says no it's not a
super it's not a stupid question if
there's an object to the left and to the
right of a black hole is it possible
that some of the light is absorbed by
the black hole and we see the fusion of
two objects is one you will see very
strange effects you will you can see the
backside of a black hole at the front
yes so you will have the warping of
light around a black hole okay and uh
you may see objects get stretched out
apparently stretched out and you could
see two objects get combined because of
the way light light travels in curved
paths around a black hole it's not a
stupid question it's actually a very
good question so yes you could see two
objects appear appear to merge
together because of gravitational
lensing yeah so it it will certainly
happen you will have these distortions
of light and because of light traveling
in curved paths around black holes okay
I'm going to end it over here today I
apologize to everybody else whose
questions I could not take but uh there
are so many other questions but I'm
going to end it over here and I'm going
to keep doing this these sessions and
I'll take as many as possible going
forward in the future on an ongoing
basis so thank you so much for all your
questions thank you so much for watching
for participating and I will see you
very soon in the next live stream please
keep learning please keep asking
questions and please keep raising your
standards thank you so much see you very
soon